<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The way to the peace and settlement of these nations, fully discovered in two letters, delivered to his late Highnesse, and one to the present Parliament, as also one to his Highnesse Richard Lord Protector, of England, Scotland, and Ireland, &amp;c. Wherein the liberty of speaking ... is opposed against Antichrist, for the procuring of his downfall, who will not grant the same to others; and now published to awaken the publick spirits in England, and to raise up an universal magistrate in Christendome, that will suffer all sorts of people, (of what religion soever they are) in any one countrey, as God (the great magistrate) suffers the same in all countreys of the world. By Peter Cornelius, Van Zurick-Zee, a lover of truth and peace.</title>
            <author>Plockhoy, Pieter Corneliszoon, fl. 1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90786</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2581E</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E972_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203156</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863217</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863217</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115406</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90786)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115406)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 144:E972[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The way to the peace and settlement of these nations, fully discovered in two letters, delivered to his late Highnesse, and one to the present Parliament, as also one to his Highnesse Richard Lord Protector, of England, Scotland, and Ireland, &amp;c. Wherein the liberty of speaking ... is opposed against Antichrist, for the procuring of his downfall, who will not grant the same to others; and now published to awaken the publick spirits in England, and to raise up an universal magistrate in Christendome, that will suffer all sorts of people, (of what religion soever they are) in any one countrey, as God (the great magistrate) suffers the same in all countreys of the world. By Peter Cornelius, Van Zurick-Zee, a lover of truth and peace.</title>
                  <author>Plockhoy, Pieter Corneliszoon, fl. 1659.</author>
                  <author>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</author>
                  <author>Cromwell, Richard, 1626-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Daniel White, and are to be sold at his shop at the seaven-Starres, in Pauls Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "march. 4. March. 4. 1658".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115406:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE WAY TO THE PEACE AND SETTLEMENT OF THESE NATIONS, Fully diſcovered in two Letters, delivered to his late Highneſſe, and one to the preſent Parliament, As alſo one to his Highneſſe <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Protector, of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEREIN</hi> The liberty of ſpeaking (which every one deſires for himſelfe) is oppoſed againſt Antichriſt, for the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his downfall, who will not grant the ſame to others;</p>
            <p>And now publiſhed To awaken the publick ſpirits in <hi>England,</hi> and to raiſe up an univerſal Magiſtrate in Chriſtendome, that will ſuffer all ſorts of people, (of what Religion ſoever they are) in any one Countrey, as God (the great Magiſtrate) ſuffers the ſame in all Countreys of the world.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 5.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Men do not light a candle, and put it under a buſhel, but on a candlesticke, and it giveth light unto all that are in the houſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Peter Cornelius, Van Zurick-Zee,</hi> a lover of truth and peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Daniel White,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> at the ſeaven-Starres, in <hi>Pauls</hi> Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h-Yard. 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:115406:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115406:2"/>
            <head>To the High and Honourable Aſſembly of PARLIAMENT, repreſenting the whole body of the Common-Wealth of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Lords, and Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving ſeen that Policy, and Religion, which (as God is) ought to be univerſall was divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and ſevered into many Sects, my ſpirit was much troubled; and looking round-about me, where to make a beginning to rectifie thoſe evils, I found no better object in Chriſtendome, then his late <hi>Highneſs</hi> the <hi>Lord PROTECTOR;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I reſolved for a while, to leave my family and native Country, fearing if I ſhould not mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to the Magiſtrates in <hi>England,</hi> what was upon my ſpirit, that they (having much to doe with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther affairs) might through the ſubtilty of the Clergy, (as in other Nations) eaſily be deceived. Therefore coming to <hi>London,</hi> I made firſt my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe to ſome of the Counſel, and ſo (by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of them) to his <hi>Highneſs</hi> were I delivering the two following Letters, was heard ſeveral times with patience; doing my endeavour to preſerve <hi>England</hi> from that great diſhonour which hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen other Nations, by ſetting up inſtead of the form, and doctrine of Chriſt, the forms and facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men. But being obſtructed in my proceeding,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115406:3"/>
through the unexpected death of his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> I was put to ſome ſtop, waiting for a better oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, and hearing, that your <hi>Honours</hi> were to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble together upon the 27. of <hi>January,</hi> my ſpirit was revived, hoping that my deſign (for the peace, and welfare of theſe Nations) by that means (bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then heretofore) might be accompliſhed. Whereupon I reſolved to bring the buſineſſe (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly propounded to his <hi>Highneſs</hi>) to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours Conſideration, being perſwaded in my heart, if You (who are now intruſted with the weighty affairs of theſe Nations) have fixed your eyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, as the eyes of the good people in theſe and other Nations are fixed upon You, that the Propoſals laid down in the two following Letters, will have a great influence upon your hearts; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if you conſider and remember the notable words of <hi>Solomon,</hi> where he ſpeaks to the Kings and Rulers of the earth, that a ſharp judgement ſhall come upon them that are in high places; for mercy will ſoon pardon the meaneſt, but mighty men (not ſtanding in the Counſel of God) ſhall be mightily tormented. Therefore give ear to him, you that rule the people, and glory in the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Nations; for he ſhall try your works, and ſearch out your Counſels: Set your ſelves as true ſervants of the Common wealth (in oppoſition to the Antichriſt) againſt all oppreſſors, that ſo they that ſeek with <hi>Haman</hi> to deſtroy and trample upon the innocent (contrary to their expectation) may be diſappointed. Let ſome courſe be taken that all perſons may buy their eſtates free from Tithes,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115406:3"/>
that thereby henceforth none in all your Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may be forced to pay Tithes to the Miniſters, for that hath been, and is ſtill the chiefe cauſe of perſecution, and diſcontent in theſe, and other Nations.<note place="margin">☜</note> 
               <hi>Suffer by no means (you having reſpect to the Honour of Chriſt) that any Confeſſion of Faith be ſet upon the Throne, as equal with the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; for Confeſſions are only to diſtinguiſh one Sect from another.</hi> Aſſiſt not with the ſword, or money of the Common-wealth any Sect, or perſon in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, that you may not hinder the truth (which hath been long kept under) from manifeſting it ſelfe by it's own power; for Magiſtrates (as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates) have no permiſſion to favour any Sect, or perſon in particular, if any of them (being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as a private perſon) will be a member of a particular Congregation, he hath his liberty, as wel as others, and may honour the ſame with his preſence, with his tongue, with his pen, and with his owne money; but not with the ſword or money of the Common-wealth: for the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates (being choſen by the generality of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) are to ſtand immoveable in the Centre, (as Moderators) between all Sects: They are in regard of their office, as treaſurers, who are intruſted with a ſum of money to imploy the ſame, not for their own, or any ones private advantage in particular, but for the benefit of all thoſe that have intruſted them; if it were the magiſtrates worke to ſet up a National Miniſtry according to their own will, then we ſhould be in danger to have as many religions, as there be ſeverall wayes of government in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115406:4"/>
world, and the Magiſtrates changing their opinion, the whole Nationall Miniſtry muſt alſo as often be changed: What is that, then, but to do his own will, inſtead of the will of God, and to have his pleaſure upon the ſouls of men. It were better, and belongs eſpecially to your office, not to follow the traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men, but to examine and reforme the Laws now in force, and to diſanull ſuch as are deſtructive and without mercy; contrary to the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the revealed will of God: which ought to be in all ages, and in all Countreys, only our rule. It is alſo your honours work and buſineſs, diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conſider, what properly belongs to the office of a Magiſtrate, before you put the ſword, and power of theſe Nations into their hands: for through want of care in ſo weighty a matter, the whole Common-wealth is in danger (as in times paſt) to fall under the dominion of one particular Sect, whoſe Miniſters (to bring the common-people, and ſo the Magiſtrates, under their juriſdiction) are commonly infecting with their forms, not only the publick meeting-places, and the houſes of the poor, or hoſpitalls. but alſo the Schools (called Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities) which have by the ſubtilty of them in all Countreys; almoſt loſt the name Univerſal, by being miſapplied to ſelf-ends and intereſts. Now to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme thoſe corruptions, it is neceſſary that the magiſtrates, (whoſe work it is to have an eye to the good of all) do expell out of thoſe publick houſes or Colledges (being builded with the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of the common-wealth) all meer humane forms of Religion, that they may not longer make a trade
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115406:4"/>
&amp; merchandize of the things of God. Granting an equall liberty to all peaceable people (as being but reaſon) that ſuch as have ventured their lives and eſtates in the time of warres, ſhould in the time of peace enjoy a like liberty with others; which may ſoon be, if you ſeriouſly conſider the things all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long propounded; not that I am come unto <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to be your inſtructer, but to bring to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours remembrance thoſe very things, which have been upon your own hearts, in order to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of ſuch a generall liberty, as hath been for many years of late pretended unto; being the only way wherein you may expect the bleſſing of God upon you, and your poſterity, againſt all oppreſſors, to the taking away of that ſhamefull reproach, that the Magiſtrates, and Miniſters, in <hi>England</hi> have brought down the King and Biſhops, rather to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in their places, then to bring the people to peace and happineſſe. If the power (to defend the good againſt the evill) in all Countreys be ordained of God, <hi>Romans</hi> 13. then reaſon requires, that all ſorts of people of what Nations ſoever, being in one Countrey together, ſhould be protected, as wel as if any of them ſeverally was in his own: which cannot be, except there be a good publick-minded and godly Magiſtrate, that will ſuffer all ſorts of people in any one Countrey, as God ſuffers the ſame in all Countreys of the world; which I expect firſt in <hi>England,</hi> and ſo from thence to break forth (as a light) to all other Countreys and Nations, as having long enough walked (as in the night) by the glimps of particular lights. It
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115406:5"/>
is time that the univerſal work of God (as the Sun) do out-ſhine all that is particular; to which end I implore the preſence of the moſt high God, to be in your Aſſembly to guide and direct your hearts in all thoſe things, that may be acceptable unto him, and moſt agreeable to his good will and pleaſure.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours, and all mens humble ſervant,</hi> Peter Cornelius, V. Z.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 24. <hi>of Jan.</hi> 1659. Hollands <hi>ſtile.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Give ear to the poor, for the cry of them is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great in theſe Nations.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>Peter Cornelius, V. Z.</hi> (together with ſome other lovers of the common good) <hi>to the Mighty, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, Farre-renowned</hi> (yet mortal) <hi>Lord Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Cromwell, Protector of England, Scotland, and Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> For the promoting of good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement, wiſheth long life, wiſdome, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing Councellors of State, to the end, that his actions may tend, not onely to the convincing of all that envy him, but that alſo he may be a light, and an example to all Dominions, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the world.</head>
            <p>WOrthy, and (as I hope) favourable Lord, being come into <hi>England</hi> during the time of your free government, I have with much chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115406:5"/>
beheld the great freedome, which this Nation (ſince the putting down the authority of Biſhops) doth enjoy, which I hope by degrees, will more and more prevaile in the world, to the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away of all force upon Conſciences, that men may be led and governed by reaſon, as men, and not as beaſts, by compulſive power. And that thoſe who are once delivered from the Antichriſtian Captivity, may not be taken Captive again by others; who, together with the great Antichriſt, ſeek their own greatneſſe; It is moſt highly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that the Example of Chriſt (to reconcile all into one) ſhould be followed; for thoſe that force the Conſcience, being not able to bring all under them by worldly power, do commonly manifeſt their own inclination to be void of Chriſtian love, and forbearance, by gathering into Sects and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, ſo that beſides the great Antichriſt, there are many little Antichriſts, that endeavour to riſe up. None of which, being able to endure any oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or gainſaying, do ſeek to gain, and draw a part of Chriſtendome under their juriſdiction. On the contrary, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath taken cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity captive: That is, put thoſe to ſhame that held others Captive, by his Aſcention into heaven, and gave gifts unto men, that they ſhould not be led aſtray again, <hi>viz.</hi> he gave as means to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, Paſtors, and Teachers; whoſe doctrine alone, while it is yet through Gods mercy; as a meaſuring line or clue of thred in the world, we ſhould ſet that on the Throne, treading under foot, all meer humane tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115406:6"/>
as Idolatry: That ſo all Chriſtendome, being divided into divers Sects (as formerly the <hi>Jews</hi> were) a generall way of Church-meeting may be inſtituted, for the hearing of Gods word read unaltered and unſophiſticated, leaving a freedome for all Sects, as well the one as the other to aſſert their owne apprehenſions and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings upon the Leſſons of their Maſter Chriſt, without being tyed to one anothers opinions.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">☞</note>For it belongs only to God and Chriſt to have dominion over Conſciences, and to Magiſtrates to prevent any from exerciſing Lordſhip over the Conſciences of others; in ſo doing they would be true maintainers and defenders of Liberty, when they uſe not their power againſt thoſe that aſſert their own meanings, but againſt thoſe that would compel others to be of their opinions. For this, <hi>viz.</hi> to deal equally in matters of Religion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſubjects, is not only good and pious, but is alſo the foundation of a good Government. Whereas otherwiſe, when one Sect ſhall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged and commended to the Church, and the other excluded, then jealouſie and envy will ſpoil all; ſo that the Magiſtrate in ſtead of being belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, may often fear that their State will be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and at length totally deſtroyed; eſpecially, when that one party is become numerous, or do joyn with a forraign or homebred enemy. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though they ſhould want the fear of God, yet for their own peace-ſake, they ſhould give free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to all: and the rather ſeeing thereby the nobleſt and beſt of underſtanding, are from all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115406:6"/>
places invited and convened in: for whoſe wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſake (as of <hi>Joſephs</hi> in Aegypt) without reſpect of perſons, they ought to be ſuffered to come in by the Magiſtrate for the common good and welfare. So that there may not only be a refining in Civil, or Politick, but chiefly in ſpirituall matters. For as formerly amongſt the Jews, (when men began to believe that the Prieſts under the Law could not erre, as to their Inſtitutions and Traditions) Gods commands were made void or of no effect: After the ſame manner alſo hath it been ſince the time of the Apoſtles in Chriſtendom, that inſtead of the holy Scriptures only (having been confirmed by Miracles) which ſhould be held a rule of Faith; yet ſome (being lovers of themſelves) have taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them a dominion, jointly with Chriſt, giving out, that men muſt believe and hold for true, what ever the Church, (<hi>viz.</hi> the Biſhops, or other ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendents thereof) do declare as truth. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people not perceiving (by reaſon of the great reſpect which they bear to thoſe that are ſet over them) that ſome of them ſeek to make themſelves great, they have ſoon attempted to hold forth the authority of the Scriptures, according to their own ſenſe; upon which when they have introduced matters contrary to reaſon, and people have refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to receive them for authentick, they have by their acquired authority kindred the people, from ſo much as to ſpeak or whiſper againſt it; conſtraining them to believe what they ſay, and alſo to rely upon them and their abſolution: and to take away all ſcruple from the people, have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115406:7"/>
out that they will anſwer for them at the day of judgement; Yea moreover (which is far more terrible) will undertake to pawn their ſouls for theirs. By which perſwaſions, the people being in anxiety fal into their boſomes, (as in former times) in their groſſe darkneſs, oppugning the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and the conſciences of ſome, with greater earneſtneſſe, are reſiſted and rejected. Yet theſe men being driven out by Tyranny, and ſeperated from Popery, have commonly ſomething of that ſower-leaven remaining in them, to bind others to their opinions, making, as a foundation of their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, new forms, over and beſides the holy Scriptures: whereby they have not exalted Chriſt but themſelves: they have not held cloſe to that only name, which was given for men to be ſaved by; but many names, as heads of parties (according to the different forms) they have brought into the world. Whence great ſtrangeneſſe, making of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, yea, ſometimes war, and horrible blood-ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings have enſued: which have been managed, not for the ſake of the holy Scriptures, (which they all held for truth) but to keep up their own opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: till again, ſome more underſtanding men per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the various differences of the forms and wayes, and the miſchief and wicked diſturbance, which this ſtrife and variance, in writings of diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and controverſie hath produced, have juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejected all names and rules, beſides the name and rule of Jeſus Chriſt, living among them, as men full of love and forbearance; whoſe underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and life, claſh not againſt the holy Scriptures
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115406:7"/>
and found reaſon: although they differ among themſelves in apprehenſions upon ſome places of the Scripture, but do continue in brotherly love and unity; by which forbearance they do not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet others in the right way (ſo farre as they are in the truth) but are alſo by others brought out of the way, wherein they themſelves did erre: a thing which ought to bear ſway with all men, according to the words of Chriſt <hi>(As you would that men ſhould do unto you, ſo do you unto them alſo)</hi> that they ſhould bear with one anothers opinions and conceptions, as they would themſelves be born withall in theirs. For it hath more the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance and appearance of compelling the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and of Tyranny, then of Reaſon, to preſs any one to come up to anothers apprehenſion, as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, before he can apprehend it with his own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to be good and neceſſary.</p>
            <p>This hath been in former ages the policy of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors, and makers of Sects and Schiſmes; who not only have caſt out by their power, ſuch, whoſe underſtanding they could not bring to agree with theirs: but being unable to do it, have made great broils, rents, and diviſions in the world; whereas e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one (ſince God is ſo long ſuffering) ought with conſtant perſevering love (without deſpairing in the work) to labour according to their power to enlighten others, that are in darkneſſe. For if thoſe that have the light reject others, or depart from them; then the blind having no good leaders, muſt needs go aſtray, and being led by the blind fall into a deep abyſſe of Ignorance. On the contrary, all
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115406:8"/>
true lovers of the common good, do labour not only to take out of the world Factions, but alſo all humane inventions (as much as in them lieth) that ſo the Lord Jeſus may alone remain Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; whoſe ſayings they bear great honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto, although they poſſibly cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the meaning of ſome particulars; yet being confirmed by ſignes and wonders; do hold the ſame for good and true. In which thing as to the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of man, they will put no truſt or affiance in any beſides Jeſus Chriſt; nor yet receive any thing as truth, but that which they themſelves can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend to be good and agreeable to his doctrine; therefore do they themſelves not ſet up or own any authority, whereby men ſhould rely upon it, nor yet ſhould give any others Authority whereby to draw men into their party, but ſhould bind all men unto Jeſus Chriſt, whom they acknowledge only for Head and Saviour.</p>
            <p>We deſire from the bottome of our hearts, that all men might be gathered together under that one name, and that your Highneſs (from whom al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every one expects ſome ſpeciall work) will help to cleanſe the Chriſtian Religion, and worſhip of God, from all prevailing exorbitances; and to that end would inſtitute (as an eternall memoriall and example to all Dominions and Governments in the world) in every City and in every County throughout <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> one generall Chriſtian aſſembling or meeting-place, in ſuch a form, that all people may ſee one another round-about by the help of ſeats, riſing by ſteps,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115406:8"/>
having before them convenient leaning-places to read and write upon; alſo one deſk aloft on one ſide or end, to hear the holy Scriptures read at a ſet time, giving freedome after that reading, to all people, orderly to confer together, concerning the Doctrine and Inſtruction of their Lord and Maſter Chriſt: That all Lording over Conſciences being prevented, all people might come together, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out receiving any obſtruction by any human forms or contrivances, even as the Jews being divided into ſeveral Sects (as <hi>Phariſees, Saduces, Eſſeens,</hi> and <hi>Herodians,</hi> &amp;c.) met together in one Temple, ſo we would not deny any particular Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their freedome, of peaceable meeting among themſelves about the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt (as the Orders or Synagogues of the Jews were not at all infringed) nor bereave the Miniſters or Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of their benefit, which they receive (of their own people) for their maintainance: for they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a fit opportunity, may the better bring in their ſenſe with others, into this generall Church-meeting. That ſo the truth getting enlargement, the honeſt party may be reſolved into unity, and the bad (that cannot indure the light) may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, and made known; who only ſeeking Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and rule, ſhould not by any means be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in high places, in matters civil or ſpiritual; that ſo the ſeat of Government may not be uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by their Adherents, when things go contrary to their minds (being cruell Wolves) who in ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their advantage, wil not ſpare the flock, over which the Rulers (who ſhould be placed to keep
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115406:9"/>
the people in order) ought eſpecially to take care, that they do not hinder them from the liberty of ſpeaking freely; as it happeneth commonly in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular aſſemblies or congregations, contrary to the laudable practice of the Jews, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.15. who themſelves, after the reading of the Scriptures, did invite and ſtir up <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> (being ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers) to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>Hence when underſtandings might be ſo free and uninterrupted, there would not only ariſe a clearing of the underſtanding, and reforming of the lives of people; but alſo a yielding, ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, condeſcending love: for the wiſeſt and exper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt men daily coming thus together, to teach and to be taught; it would incline the hearts of thoſe that ſhould behold them, one towards another, which we may diſcern in worldly matters, (as in making of Treaties or Peace with Nations) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as otherwiſe they being drawn up, and ſtretched beyond their preſent apprehenſions, by the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Authority, they ſtand upon their guard in oppoſition to one another, as well in ſpirituall as Civil affairs. This now being ſo, it will eſpecially concern your Highneſs, whilſt the eyes of all are fixed upon you, to ſet a compleat Example, that all people <hi>(that do ſlander you, as to have no Religion)</hi> may evidently perceive, that you do only maintain the Chriſtian Religion, and not Countenance any other particular name or Head whatſoever. For Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, the only heavenly Teacher, (who hath been long enough trod under foot by Sectarians) ought to be ſet up above all; and that all men as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115406:9"/>
be joyned together, is the only way to abol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh all Lording over Conſciences; which hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready driven him out of his ſeat, and many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years ſince poſſeſſed his place, that at length the ſpirituall uſurpation, with its Antichriſtian Dominion, may be laid down at his feet.</p>
            <p>Thus doing you will be accounted a follower of the example of the good King <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23. who to reform the Jews worſhip of God, threw down all <hi>Chimerims</hi> and Idolatry, and brought forth the book of the old Covenant, to the ears of the people; and all the people ſtood in that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. So will all Chriſtendome (unleſſe any would ſet up man, to rule together with Chriſt) commend your diligent and wiſe forecaſt, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection, and pray for the proſperity of your eſtate, to the ruine of the Romiſh Seat, which (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all that would force Conſciences) hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the report of this noble Freedome, will begin to tremble, yea, even their ſilenced children, whoſe mouths have been muzzled by compulſive re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, will begin to ſpeak; and ſo in time of need, ſeeing your free Government, may come to ſhrowd themſelves under your wings. To which, God the Father who beholdeth you, and all Mens actions, afford his grace, through Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115406:10"/>
            <head>To his Highneſſe <hi>Oliver</hi> Lord Protector, of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>MIghty, and (as I hope) prudent Lord, being by the Loadſtone of your free Government drawn, and come into <hi>England,</hi> I have not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the multiplicity of Opinions, and various dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of Sects (who have been long held toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a falſe peace) but alſo have laid before you an expedient (in my Letter of the 24. of <hi>June</hi>) to bring them together to a true reall unity.</p>
            <p>I hope (ſeeing the bonds of Antichriſt are in a great meaſure broken in <hi>England,</hi> by the effuſion of much blood,) that you as a ſkilful Pilot, will keep your hand at the Helm, &amp; your eye upon the ſail, that ſo the little Antichriſts, who ſeek to rule over Conſciences, may not bring your work to ſhame and reproach, by exciting you to Tyranny, and thereby obſtruct you in perfecting the ſame. For ſeverall Princes and Magiſtrates have formerly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to bring down the Antichriſt; but not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowing the nature thereof, have (unawares) not obſerved the little ones, while they oppoſe the great ones only, as Biſhops and others; and the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, ſelf-ſeeking ones to become great, have to their power helped the Magiſtracy (as if themſelves were Enemies of the ſpirituall domination) only that they might ſucceed in the others places, which evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeared as ſoon as ever they began to take breath, in that they have inſtituted new forms (the cauſe of Sects and parties) by framing new Articles
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115406:10"/>
of faith, over and beſides the holy Scripture, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſhut men up within the Park or Incloſure of their own opinions; by which means they ſet not up Chriſt in the hearts of men, but their own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Dominion, which is Idolatry. And the Rulers being brought on their ſide, oppreſſion hath been exerciſed upon ſuch as have not worſhipped their Images (I mean their contrived Forms) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out life.</p>
            <p>Now to oppoſe theſe deceitfull ſpirits, who in an Angellicall humility and lowlineſſe, come with great and lamentable complaints and petitions. The good Magiſtrates, to the end they be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, ſhould, for the protecting of the Innocent, be armed with a Divine foreſightfulneſſe, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection, for they by all means (as if the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates could make their dead Forms live) do inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly implore the interpoſing their Authority, well knowing, that there is no better way, to bring the Common-people (wherein the ſtrength of a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſts) under their juriſdiction, and do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſet the Magiſtracy (which to govern well cannot be too high) by degrees higher and higher; yea upon hopes thereby to have their Forms ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed unto) reſolve to make any body their King or Emperour; being well aſſured, that when he hath thus given up his power to them, and ſet them on the Throne, they may afterwards do with him what they will.</p>
            <p>For the moſt part all Kings have loſt their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, by giving too much Authority to the Miniſtry or Teachers, and have become (inſtead of Lords,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115406:11"/>
ſervants; yea (fearing the oppoſition of them and their followers) have for their ſakes become Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants.</p>
            <p>Conſidering theſe things, the Magiſtrates to whom (and not to the Teachers) the ſword is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, for the protection of the good, ſhould hold it faſt, to prevent and fruſtrate all cunning and ſubtil practices, and inſtead of giving Miniſters or Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers power and Authority, ſhould (by their gener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Aſſemblies ſet up in all Cities and Countries) draw the common people out of their boſomes and dominion, that they may looſe their uſurped pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that ſo the ſword may return into its right place, for which God hath ordained it, without the Magiſtrates needing in their Government, to have dependance on the Miniſters or Teachers, who are wont to incenſe the people againſt them. This (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that the whole power will come into the hands of the Magiſtrates) will bring many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands a year to the Common-wealth. For the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple having opportunity to come into the generall Aſſemblies, out of love to hear many wiſe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding men, will not need to give maintainance to the hirelings, who Lord it in particular Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whereby the Magiſtrates (who now begin to lighten or eaſe the burthen of maintainance) will be beloved more then formerly. Then ſhall we firſt be able rightly to diſcern, when the power is come into its right place, what the Magiſtrates are, who now many times are accounted oppreſſors, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Governours: though it may be that oppreſſion and evill government doth proceed more from the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115406:11"/>
nature of the Teachers, then of the Magiſtrates, who (now the way to make the Teachers power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe is opened) will begin to appear more evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then formerly, and the more, becauſe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon aſſembling place may be inſtituted for draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the people from the Miniſters in all places, without compulſion of any man, bringing all Sects (without giving wages to any) as brethren to equal priviledges. But if thoſe that are of one and the ſame opinion, will have particular Congregations, and Set-Miniſters, let themſelves pay them as a Maſter doth his ſervant. For its no reaſon that a man ſhould help to maintain anothers ſervants; eſpecially, if they be ſuch as (in his judgement) are ſoul-deſtroyers; who (being in his ſenſes) would aſſiſt ſuch enemies as do countermine him? Is it not to be wondred at, that the Miniſters (who would be eſteemed more then the Magiſtrates) ſhould (to the ſhame of their Church or Congregations) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire wages of them, for whom they have not labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? Neither is it the mark of a true Church, where the Members thereof are ſo covetous, and unmercifull, that they will not maintain or provide for their own Miniſters; and the Teachers (loving the wages of unrighteouſneſſe) do (contrary to the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Commandement) covet the goods of others; whereof the Apoſtles and their Congregations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> would have been aſhamed to think, much leſſe would do it. Yet I hope, that once the Conſcience-burthening-law of conſtraining to pay Tithes to the Miniſters (who ſeek rather after Lucre then the Truth) for the reſt of theſe Nations, will be made
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115406:12"/>
null and void. Some courſe being taken to ſupply the neceſſities of the Miniſters, who by ſuch Act (that none ſhall be forced to pay Tithes to them) may be brought to a want of a ſubſiſtance; and yet that this may be ſo done, only for thoſe that are now made deſtitute, but no encouragement for any others in time to come. And by this the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates (while every Sect maintain their own Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters) will be freed from laying ſuch intollerable burthens on their Subjects, having to provide for none elſe, but thoſe, who are appointed in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſemblies or meeting-places, to read the holy Scriptures, and keep the people in order; to ſhew that they are no maintainers of Sects, but of the Chriſtian Religion; being as Fathers and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diators, to bring the good together, out of all Sects, to unite under the name of Jeſus, to the end that his Kingdome and Government may be enlarged, for an example to <hi>Holland, Denmark, Sweden, France,</hi> and other Kingdomes, who ſeeing there is no force nor conſtraint uſed, will eaſily be brought to a firm bond of Unity. This being the only means by forſaking all Men, and human-Forms, to be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Chriſt (whoſe honour only is ſought) againſt the Antichriſt, contrary to the way of other Kings and Princes, who being ſeparated from Popery, have made themſelves unworthy of the bleſſing of Chriſt, by giving honour to the bare name of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Calvin,</hi> and others, inſtead of giving it to Chriſt, having been deceived by the little Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts their followers; who as well as the great one, ſeek their own glory; eaſe, and idleneſſe; and as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115406:12"/>
if they had no fellowſhip with the great Antichriſt, have put the holy Scriptures into the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hands, which was before was prohibited to be read, only ſeeking that we ſhould agree with them in their Forms, applying and fitting themſelves (ſuch is their ſubtilties, to the temper of the times: as a Fowler gives ſcope to a Bird he hath already in a ſtring, that ſo at length it may be content to live in a Cage. Now againſt theſe little Antichriſts, who under the name of giving liberty, would bind the people to their opinions) the Magiſtrates (being taught by experience) ſhould as wel counter-work, as againſt the great, that they may come to the very root, bringing the holy Scripture (which was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly prohibited to be read) with great Triumph into the generall Aſſembly or meeting-place, and ſet it on high, to the end that the found or report of this, to wit, that Chriſt alone muſt rule (by his word) in the hearts of men, among all Nations (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the great work done in <hi>England</hi>) may be heard, giving liberty to every one, after the reading of the Scripture (contrary to the little An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, who wil have it underſtood only according to their own Forms and Expoſitions) to ſet forth his own apprehenſion, without being bound to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ones opinion: That ſpirituall matters being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to ſpiritual, Antichriſt may be ſtormed with two Armies, <hi>viz.</hi> the Truth againſt Error, and the materiall ſword againſt oppreſſors, who by their arrogating diſpoſition and excluſion of others, do ſeek to reſtrain the liberty of ſpeaking, which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers the errors of the underſtanding for the cure
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115406:13"/>
thereof. Whereas, by ſtopping the mouths of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (as heretofore) they make men incureable.</p>
            <p>Now to further this, that the weakneſſe or Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſome may be remedied by the knowledge of others, without diſturbance or Confuſion, it will be neceſſary that the Authority of the Magiſtrate interpoſe in this generall Aſſemby or meeting-place, that every one may ſpeak in their order, ſtaying their time, and thoſe that break order, may (after due warning) be ejected, till they are better diſpoſed, without oppreſſing them by Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>This would be glad tiding, yea, a true year of Jubilee, for thoſe that lye in priſon, only for aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their opinions in matters of Religion; that now they may (together with others) bring in their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings into this generall Aſſembly, to receive or give light. And to the end, that Antichriſt (or he that exalts himſelf above others) may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſhut out, it is exactly to be obſerved, that no preheminence or ſole priviledge be granted to any, (of offering any thing, or of ſpeaking firſt) that ſo every one being at liberty and unhindered, may bring forth that which is moſt conducing to the Common welfare, according to the words of <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.16. All of them ſitting ſtill, ſo long after the reading of the Scriptures (as being ſwift to hear and ſlow to ſpeak) till any one think it fit (in his judicious and humble mind) to propoſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what for mutuall edification; endeavouring with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to make his diſcourſe ſhort, that another may have his turn likewiſe, contrary to the cuſtome of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115406:13"/>
the common Teachers, who only, or ſolely ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, do lengthen out their diſcourſe, to the weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their Auditory; for which end the Moder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ators (who ought to be meek and underſtanding men) are to obſerve that there be due order kept.</p>
            <p>This (ſeeing no Forms or Articles are made in it beſides the holy Scripture) will be a Councel and Synod, ſtanding alwayes open, to all rational peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, without impoſing any mans concluſions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the former Aſſemblies, who have excluded all Nations and Poſterity (by their ſelf conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) dividing people, as by a wall of ſeparation, one from another, by their Forms: whereupon great eſtrangement hath enſued, as if they were different Nations. And the better to ſet up their Antichriſtian Kingdom and dominion, have ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived their Catechiſmes, that they have bound up, and ſo ſpoiled the underſtandings of their children, before they come to have the uſe of Reaſon, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their dependants or Members, captive under them in their Net, as beaſts, contrary to the order of their Creation: well knowing, that if they gave them the liberty of ſpeaking, they would not be long worſhipped as Idols, or ſacrificed to, as Bell at <hi>Babell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Contrariwiſe, people, in the general Aſſemblies, when all underſtandings and tongues are free, will be ſtirred up to the exerciſe thereof, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring together, will come to knowledge, love, and familiarity. The truth (which hath been long kept under or with held in unrighteouſneſs) will ſcatter the lyes, as light doth darkneſſe, and the great cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115406:14"/>
which we have given to ſome Teachers in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, will by oppoſition be diminiſhed, and the power of all Sects; (the one diſpelling the Errors of the other) will be broken.</p>
            <p>This will be the place, where we ſhall diſcern &amp; learn to know, the moſt wiſe as <hi>Solomon,</hi> and meek as <hi>Moſes;</hi> which out of all Sects (only ſuch as ſeek to domineer over others excluded) may be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as Councellors,<note place="margin">The Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates from the higheſt to the loweſt, ought to be men of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>its for their work (concerning their office) is not a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, but a general work.</note> to keep ſteady the ballance of Government, without reſpect of perſons, to the end, that the Spirit of God be not confined; which will be a ſure mark, that Wiſdome (for the ſake of which Kings in times paſt were bleſſed) is under this Government eſteemed above gold and ſilver; being the principall to diſtinguiſh all things, chiefly Policy from Religion, for the common good: For Magiſtrates (if they would remain without uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Office of Chriſt) may not make Laws in matters of Religion, but againſt evill deeds, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the good: To the end, that their Subjects (from whom they receive Taxes and Impoſitions) may be protected in peace, of what Religion ſoever they are: For the power to puniſh evil-doers, is ordained of God in all Lands, without reſpect of Religion, and whoſoever oppoſeth that power, oppoſeth the Ordinance of God; not that all Officers (though they rule ill) are of God, or are his Miniſters, but thoſe only, who adminiſter their Office rightly, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods will: Otherwiſe, thoſe who here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore have riſen up againſt Tyrants, oppoſing their perſons, ſhould have been indeed oppoſers of Gods Ordinance: contrary to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115406:14"/>
13. who hath ſaid, that ſuch as are continually im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the defence of the good, are the Miniſters of God, untill they have by falſe Teachers, been drawn beſides their Office, to domineer over Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and ſo brought into the ſervice or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of Satan, to the grief of their Subjects.</p>
            <p>But I hope, that once the ſword, which hath been with-held from lyers and oppreſſors, ſhall cut them off together with the Cable of their hope (the Tithes) that ſo the ground of almoſt all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion being taken away, not only the Subjects, but alſo the Magiſtrates, may live in peace; who are now continually liable to hear the complaints of the head Sectaries, who ſeek to domineer over others, it being the nature of ſuch, who finding their own weakneſſe, do make power and force their refuge, contrary to the example of Chriſt and the Primitive Saints, whoſe ſtrength was only the evidence of truth. Wherefore all people (and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Magiſtrates) are to take heed that they aſſiſt not lyes, uſing their power (according to Gods Ordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) only againſt thoſe that are to the prejudice of good Government, or the hurt of mankind in generall, without mingling Pollicy, and Religion, which were ordained for ſeverall ends; the one to defend the good men againſt the evil, and the other to make the evill good. There remains only, that the Magiſtrates (for an example to their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects) do null all humane commanding and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining-Laws in ſpirituall matters, <hi>that ſo all plants, which the heavenly Father hath not planted, may (according to the ſaying of Chriſt) be rooted up,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115406:15"/>
which will beſt take effect when the dominion of the Teachers, is through the power of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, come to an end; and their hope of domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering over others cut off.<note place="margin">☞</note> 
               <hi>For Magiſtrates, inſtead of Lording it over Conſciences, ought on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to hinder all Lordſhip over Conſciences,</hi> that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining and murmuring may come to an end, and that the righteous may rejoyce.</p>
            <p>For which end, that we may tranſmit the World unto our poſterity, in a better condition then we firſt found it, I have contributed this little to my power.</p>
            <p>I beſeech your Highneſs, let not any preingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment oblige you, to what you may afterwards ſee inconſiſtant with the Magiſtrates true intereſt, with the due liberty of Gods people, and the free propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Goſpel. It were better for you and more for your Honour with <hi>Ahaſhuerus,</hi> to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict your own hand and Seal, then with <hi>Herod,</hi> to perform a raſh engagement.</p>
            <p>But while it is yet in your Highneſs choice, let not the right hand of brave Atchievments for the vindication of liberty be ever ſtained with autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing (to the honour of men, and diſhonour of Chriſt) any Confeſſion of Faith, Ordinance, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree; which will in the leaſt intrench thereon, or indulge the enemies thereof. Be not deceived, by ſuch perſons as pretend to advance your Honour, as in the time of <hi>Daniel</hi> was done to King <hi>Darius,</hi> that the good people in thoſe and other Nations, may not be diſappointed of their hope and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations in you.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115406:15"/>I do wiſh for concluſion, that your Highneſs, and all your Counſellors of State, to the bringing down of Antichriſt, and all his Adherents, may have a great heart, and humble under God and Chriſt. That the great work done in <hi>England,</hi> come not to the Honour of a mortal man, but to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of him, who hath received the power over the Kingdomes of the earth.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Be wiſe as Serpents, and innocent as Doves, <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 10.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <closer>O Lord of all Lords, and Magiſtrates, teach them that rule as Gods in the world, to conſider, that they are but men in thy eyes; That they may handle their Subjects after ſuch a manner, as they wiſh to be handled by thee in thy judgement.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To his Highneſs <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Protector of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Peter Cornelius</hi> wiſheth, an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall and unbiaſed heart, to the end he may as a true Moderator ſo hold the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance in the Government, that one Sect may not domineer over the other.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nexpected,</hi> yet (I hope) <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> Lord Protector,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEing come into <hi>England</hi> in love, to the common good, I have after much longing ſeverall times had opportunity to ſpeak with your Father about
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115406:16"/>
divers matters, to whom alſo I delivered two Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which he promiſed to conſider of, and was willing I ſhould have liberty further to declare my mind and ſenſe unto him: this being prevented by his unexpected death, I have thought fit foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as your Highneſs hath ſucceeded him, to transfer the aforementioned Letters to you, hoping that my counſell (which your Father did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe) being joyned with your power and goodneſs, will order all things in ſuch a way that the light of liberty kindled in <hi>England,</hi> may enlighten all Kingdomes and Governements in the world.</p>
            <p>Your Highneſs is not ignorant how the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Biſhops have held many thouſands, in theſe, and other Countreys, together in a falſe Peace by the bands of Tyranny, untill ſome mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous ſpirits (not able any longer to bear that injuſtice) did with a ſtrong arme, throw of the Tyrannicall yoak, by reaſon whereof the falſe peace, being thus interrupted the people is become divided into many kinds of Sects and opinions, which yet is better then to have them bound toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a falſe peace, with the bands of Tyranny, for the diſeaſes as well of the mind, as of the body, cannot be cured unleſſe they be firſt manifeſted, neither would he do the part of a ſkilfull Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, that ſhould endeavour to ſkin over the wound, without cleanſing the bottome, but rather diſcover his baſe deſigne in preferring his own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt before the health &amp; welfare of the Patient, for this cauſe it will be good to ſuffer every one without any let or hinderance, to manifeſt his ſence
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115406:16"/>
and diſeaſe (as well in ſpirituall as bodily matters) to the very bottome, that ſo the corruptions being found out, the remedy for cure of the ſame may be applyed, to which purpoſe that every error might meet with its Antidote; I did in my Letters delivered to your Father, propound the ſetting up a generall meeting-place, in all Cityes and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes, which might ſtand as a clear light between all Sects, for the diſpelling of errors; not by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, but by the power of Scripture and reaſon, without binding up the liberty of ſpeaking, (whereby the defects of the underſtanding are kept hidden) which is already much laboured after by the little Antichriſts, that ſeek their own greatneſs, but I hope that you, perceiving the miſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, will above all things remember <hi>Englands</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, which hath coſt much blood, and with a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous ſpirit bring down all deſignes how ſubtil ſoever, without being deceived, by ſuch as come in ſheeps-cloathing, with ſmooth and flattering words, and in a fair and ſpecious outſide, ſhew themſelves like Angels of light, againſt whom you ought as wel to be armed with prudence, as againſt open enemies, that ſo the ſword which is given for the protection of the good, may not be abuſed by thoſe who have more hopes to prevaile with you, then they had with your Father, who knew their diſpoſitions by long experience, yet I hope you will ſhew, and demonſtrate by your works &amp; actions, that you will in that, not only follow, but exceed the Exampler of your Father, by not eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing any particular Sect, (which in other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115406:17"/>
hath cauſed a total deſtruction of liberty) but by maintaining a tolleration for all; For the Lord of heaven hath not deſigned <hi>England,</hi> for a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular but for a generall work, therefore it is one of the main buſineſſes of Magiſtrates, to try the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of thoſe that repaire to them, for there are two kinds of Spirits that ſtand in direct oppoſition, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes working the one for their own particular, and the other for the common good, not only to cure the diſtempers of the mind, but alſo to take off the burthens and afflictions of the body, and when you are at a loſſe, ſtand centred in the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls will, who can make way for true wiſdom, to direct and lead you in and out, before the people. Thus having born teſtimony againſt all oppreſſion, I leave it to God, your Self, and your Counſel, not doubting but if it ſhould prove ineffectual God will raiſe up inſtruments for delivering of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>and ſubſcribe my ſelf to be, A well wiſher of Englands liberty, and all other Nations happineſſe,</hi> Peter Cornelius, <hi>Van-Zurick-Zee.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <p>A mercifull man (being ſenſible of the poverty and afflictions of others) cannot be in peace before he have done his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour (according to his power) to eaſe the burdens and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of the opreſſed: therefore have I, to diſcharge my duty, in another <hi>Treatiſe</hi> (which is to be publiſhed) propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a way to make the poor diſtreſſed people, in theſe, and other Nations happy.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
